welcome to business ends i'm ralph rivas
for today's episode we have richard
bates manulife president and ceo hi
richard
hi ralph how are you doing thank you
very much for having me here
now i want to talk about the impact of
the pandemic on the economy and in
particular the insurance industry
you know uh people's uh fears have been
heightened um you know uh people have
been fearful running out of money and uh
drowning in debt because of the covet-19
pandemic so tell us um any particular
trends that you've observed during this
pandemic
yeah ralph it's a good question i mean
listen this is this has been tough it's
been a tough period for everybody uh and
uh particularly as you you recognize as
people are continuing to want to make
sure they provide the best livelihood
that they can for their family uh it's
absolutely critical now more than ever
that people are taking care of their
finances and looking after themselves
and their family and their health
there's been a few trends that we've
seen coming through
first and foremost right from the
beginning of the pandemic we saw an
increased interest in health protection
an increased interest no surprise on
making sure that people are properly
covered but also at the same time that
they make sure that they take care of
themselves both physically and
importantly mentally as well so we've
seen over the last year and a half quite
an elevated trend in that area
i mean secondly we've just completed a
study about gen wise and gen z's and the
findings from that study are also very
parallel to that and very interesting so
we're finding that a lot of millennials
continue to be interested in making sure
that they're putting their money in the
right place that it is yielding the type
of returns that they're looking for but
at the same time we have gen z's coming
through concerned about their mental
well-being concerned about their job
opportunities concerned about really um
how they will also be able to be
financially solvent and financially well
protected going forward
so what we've seen overall is despite
the challenges that we find finding in
the pandemic we are certainly seeing
that there is an elevated interest in
people making sure that look after
themselves and making sure that they're
financially as stable as feasible and
stable as possible
now that's pretty interesting gen z's um
i guess the older gen z's would be the
first one to get it right because uh
i can only imagine that um maybe their
first job is um
you know they're working from home
um they haven't really uh experienced
the uh the feel of the office so moving
forward um how does um manulife
interpret that phenomenon uh
do uh do you see this uh
hybrid work affecting everyone and
different industries differently or in
particular how does it affect um the
insurance sector
yeah and that's a really good point i
mean you've got this generation of gen
z's and if i can just take a moment my
oldest uh is 22 years old and she moved
into the workforce a couple of years ago
and within six months similar to
everybody else had moved into a work
from home structure very new and very
unusual for people to be in and i think
the the gen z's however are remarkably
well equipped to be able to handle a
hybrid type structure in terms of the
digital skill set in terms of their
capabilities really does align now in
terms of what we see in trends going
forward i think it really depends on the
industry in question so in terms of uh
we look at the life insurance sector
we're quite privileged at a place like
manulife where our customers we have a
service and we have a product that can
provide for our customers our agents our
insurance advisors at the same time have
a digital means in which they can
deliver that service and then ultimately
the company as also has a way that it
can continue to support both the
insurance advisors as well as the
customers so that all three parties can
actually stay at home and continue to be
safe uh while we ride out the pandemic
now having said that we still find that
going forward i think you will see a
more of a hybrid approach happening so
although for example manulife started
his digitalization journey way before
the pandemic and we were fortunate that
on day one of the announcement of the
lockdown in march last year we were able
to switch to 100 digital overnight in
the next in the in 24 hour period
now going forward the reality is we're
unlikely to stay 100 digital and we are
already having we have people back in
the office with agency agents going back
into their branches with agents meeting
customers when it's allowed and
permitted in their various areas they
live and so what we're seeing is a far
more hybrid approach and i think this
will be quite common certainly in our
industry as we look going forward
now actually i have some figures with me
um from your study uh it says here uh
of the younger population have started
preparing financially uh if something
happens to them uh 79 of millennials
getting their insurance plans and uh 92
percent of gen z is considering availing
their own life health and variable unit
link policy now a variable unit link
policy can you elaborate a little more
on that um what does that mean exactly
and um
um
what are the main considerations on
their preferences in particular
yeah i mean i think to me as an insurer
there are a couple of elements to this
uh the first element is making sure that
from a health and well-being you are
protected
number one priority is to make sure that
you're protecting yourself and that's
the core element of what life insurance
provides and offers
now if there is an opportunity to also
have an investment element so should
nothing happen to you over the course of
that over the course of your policy you
have some residual value left at the end
of the uh at the end of the term and the
end of the policy
now with what we are seeing in terms of
our next generation coming through they
are as mindful as any other generation
about making sure that they are putting
their money where it makes sense for
them financially but also at the same
time that they are able to make sure
that they're protecting themselves and
this is what a vul product essentially
provides is both that core element of
protection coupled with an investment
element should nothing happen to you
have an opportunity to be able to
recruit some of the investment over a
period of time
now coupled as well as that we also have
an investment management our business
which releases uitfs and we just
launched last year a uitf called a money
market fund which is a perfect entry
level for a pure investment uh um
vehicle for the next generation to be
able to be able to start investing in uh
you know fund vehicles for them to be
able to move forward now i think to me
again this is very important because
what it does is it gives that next
generation a foothold into investment as
well as the existing vol products gives
them an access and a foothold into the
protection and the insurance coupled
with the investment this gives them
essentially a broad range of suites in a
broad range of products that they can
really take advantage of as they look to
protect their health as well as also
make sure that they are investing
sensibly as they as they move forward in
their careers
yeah so that's pretty good to hear that
uh
uh my generation and the younger
generation are really looking into uh
investments i mean uh me personally um i
kind of wish that i uh started earlier
than
then
now i want to talk about uh
the uh
the impact of the pandemic on uh
manulife philippines um how are you guys
adjusting uh
are you gonna be working uh from home uh
until the year end or even until next
year um
what are your
um i don't know any silver linings that
you see during this pandemic
yeah i mean i think i think a couple of
things to to bear in mind in terms of
the workflow and how we're structured we
have roughly 15 possibly more fifteen to
twenty percent of our staff on site and
that could be either in the branches uh
or it could be inside on the office um
and meanwhile we allow and our agents
are able to come to the branch and work
from there uh as well as also work from
home so we've got enough flexibility in
our design and structure that people can
work where they feel most comfortable
now going forward the human element that
is so critical to our industry is not
going to go away an event but we need to
make sure that as we bring it together
we do it in a safe and a safe and secure
manner and that is absolutely our
priority for our agents our customers as
well as our staff and so in terms of the
hybrid approach we are seeing uh we are
having people coming into the office i'm
in the office right now for example
and we are continuing to make sure that
people are looked after and protected as
we go forward
so um
the 15 to 20
in the uh
in the office that are physically there
uh what types of uh
jobs are they doing and uh
which uh i mean do you do you can do are
you considering uh to have the flexible
work arrangement uh be put permanently
yeah it's interesting ralph because we
actually had the flexible uh working
arrangement before the pandemic
so we already have a flexible structure
already in manulife because of the
demands as we all know in the
philippines of the types of commutes
people have we had implemented this uh
going back to 2018 2019. so in fact the
shift of being able to move to what has
now been 100 almost 100 work from home
and then the future shift that allows
for a hybrid structure um that's nothing
that's particularly unusual for us and
something that we've had in place for
quite some time um to really try and
give people more control and more
flexibility about how they work
but in terms of they're going to detect
the type of functions and operations
typically we would we'd all have our uh
csos our customer service officers they
will be down in the branches being ready
to service customers who wish to walk in
and attend to things personally we also
have a lot of people in our call center
as well as our operational side
our underwriters our claims team
and various different other operations
teams but at the same time it's not
limited to just the service side of what
we do we have our um our sales support
team we i've seen our hr people uh
coming into the office the reality is
there's a limit to a lot of people of
how you know how many hours they're
comfortable doing at home and if there
is an opportunity to come in and if i'm
honest have some wi-fi have some air
conditioning get someone else to make
the coffee this just makes a difference
to how people's energy levels are and so
we encourage people to come in in a safe
and controlled environment and that's
what's really important but going
forward as i say i think the hybrid
structure we've already had in place and
as i look out over the next uh you know
as we come through the pandemic and we
come to a place where we are going to
have people return to the office more
frequently i think we will always have a
number of people who will continue to
work from home and come into the office
and take both approaches
now uh i've talked to many ceos already
and they said that the pandemic is
perhaps the most
uh challenging uh
most challenging in their career um
would you say the same to you i mean uh
would you consider the pandemic is the
most challenging um i mean this is it
this is the most challenging uh thing
that you've ever experienced uh
what what did you learn from this and uh
any uh did you did your leadership uh
style uh
change during this period
yeah good questions ralph i mean i've
often reflected on this myself
the
in terms of dependent yes it is a
challenge there's no doubt about it it's
a challenge for all leaders
but this is
irrespective of the pandemic there are
challenges of all types of leadership
and what's important is that this is why
the opportunity to step up and the
opportunity to make sure that we look
after our people look after our
customers look after the company that
exists all the time
now i i arrived here in the philippines
in the middle of 2019 and roughly six
months later a little bit a little bit
around then we moved into the pandemic
now the reality is the one thing that i
miss is not being able to see my people
as much as i'd like to the other thing i
miss is not being able to see as much of
the country as i'd like to so i only had
a chance to go out and visit about 50
of our 55 branches so i managed to get
to about 23 of our branches
before the pandemic hit so i still miss
the opportunity to get out and travel
and see those but as i um as i look at
kind of what it means for me and the
team
i'm really fortunate that i have a very
very strong leadership team around me i
am always very reliant on a leadership
team i believe that we as a team run
this company it's not just me as an
individual we as a team lead this
company and it is important that all of
us play our part and as all of us come
together and this team has been
exceptional
right from day one the moment we moved
in that we knew the wave of uh potential
lockdown was happening because i'd
observed other manulife businesses in
china in hong kong and we'd observed
this we knew that it was very likely so
we started preparing about a month or
two before the actual lockdown occurred
so when the lockdown did get announced
we were ready to move and shift and this
to me is uh so important to have the
right people around you the right people
that you can trust that you can rely on
and this is very much the way that i
like to run an organization very much
the way i like to have an inclusive
style that really brings people together
we work on each other's strengths we
rely on each other's strengths and more
importantly as a team it's helped us get
through this and i think the last year
and a half for many like philippines has
been exceptionally good
considering the circumstances and i'm
again very very proud of my people to
help us get here
now uh it's too bad that you haven't
really traveled the country or you know
you've seen the country which is just a
couple of months and then we went into a
lockdown but um
you know uh the insurance industry has
been one of those uh industries that
have been quite resilient due to the
during the pandemic but uh many other
industries are not as fortunate now
i can imagine
manual life can take in those job losses
from other industries uh can you tell us
more about that
sure very happy to i think
the as an insurance advisor that element
of our business um a lot of people make
an assumption that an insurance advisor
is a sales job it's not it is an
advisory job it is a servicing job it is
a responsibility towards a customer
throughout the entire lifecycle of a
customer and the entire life cycle of
the service that we offer them and so
actually most of the time most of the
people that we've been able to recruit
into our industry during the pandemic
time be them uh young millennials or
older who've been displaced by changing
changes in their previous industry have
very often come from service industries
it could be a hotel and tourism it could
be flight attendants it could
it could be a number of different other
sorts of banking as another sector as
well where the service element is very
strong not all of them have necessarily
had sales experience beforehand and not
all of them have certainly had financial
sales experience and that's not really
what's important what is important is
the ability to be able to understand and
learn from a customer perspective
the value of what insurance and what
investments bring to the customer and
that ability to be able to put yourself
into another person's position
hear what their challenges are and help
them shape the solution to meet that
that's the difference between a
successful insurance advisor and one
that possibly is not as successful and
so we've been fortunate enough that
we've had a number of people join us
from a number of these service
industries and this is one of the
benefits of life insurance is we are
able to have a service that is still in
demand by our customers more now more
than it's ever been and we also have a
means to deliver that service while
everyone can stay safe and that is quite
unique to our industry
an industry that has a strong purpose an
industry that has a strong uh drive to
make sure that we're looking after
people and helping them and their
families and really right now there is
now more than ever is the time for our
industry to be absolutely accountable
and absolutely reliant uh and responding
to what our customers needs are
now you mentioned that you've uh took in
people from the airline industry from
hotel and uh you know a hospitality so
uh
how many have you recruited and uh how
many more do you need and uh
maybe now's the time to
ask those that have lost their jobs that
um
this could be uh their track
yeah absolutely i mean when you look out
for the industry and i think what we're
seeing is there is always a demand for
insurance advisors in the life insurance
industry there always has been and
always will be it is part of how we grow
the industry and manulife has been here
115 years next february so we're coming
up to 115 years old we will be here for
another 115 years and in that time we
need new blood we need the new
generation coming through because the
new generation understand the needs of
their existing they understand the needs
of the of the generation that they are a
part of that they can actually help and
advise and this is why you're always
looking for new recruits always looking
for new blood to come into the industry
and to come into your organization
and this is so as we've looked through
we continue to recruit over the course
of uh since the pandemic began we
haven't slowed any of that down and we
are still very uh
very optimistic about how we continue to
grow the business and i think as an
industry and an opportunity that it
presents
particularly millennials gen z's it
really does present a huge opportunity
and a chance where you have a flexible
lifestyle a chance where you can really
help other people make a difference in
other people's lives
and there aren't that many industries
that allow you to do that we train we
educate we will support we will help you
grow and essentially that to me is such
a great opportunity for anyone that is
potentially either displaced in their
current job um or is coming out and
being a fresh graduate and looking for
an industry to move into it's a very
noble industry that has a lot of success
uh for many of our uh many of our
insurance advisors
so um
what about i mean flight attendants
those in the uh hotel and restaurants uh
what skill set i mean why them uh do
they have a particular skill sets that
they already have that could be uh
beneficial to the insurance uh companies
and uh
what other i mean i wanna i wanna know
uh for instance me
uh
what skill sets do i need to land a job
in uh the insurance uh industry
i mean ralph good question be careful
i'll be recruiting you in a minute if
you're not careful yeah
the in terms of the in terms of those
basic requirements at a minimum 18 years
old it's preferable if you have a
university degree but not necessarily
essential
that being said if you're talking about
the kind of the personalities we look
for we look for people who have who have
the ability to listen the ability to
show and and uh demonstrate a level of
empathy for their customer they've got
to understand what the customer needs
are and by listening to what the
customer needs are can shape and advise
them on what is the best way that they
can be looked after remember it's not
about just making a sale it is also
about continuing to service the customer
going through and we've had many uh
insurance advisors who've been in our
industry 20 30 years they've seen
generations grow they've they've
protected both their first customers
their customers children their customers
grandchildren we've seen them grow as
the industry has grown we've also seen
our insurance advisors buy our customers
bedside while you know may they may have
been in hospital in a difficult period
of their life with a health issue seeing
them and making sure that they're going
through the journey together
that listening skill that ability to be
connected with people is so important
and this is why people coming from the
service industry is all
very often are trained in a way also
developed and plus they have a natural
inclination to wish to serve and that
really makes a difference on the type of
successful people who can uh who can
work in the insurance sector and of
course uh news reporters as well ralph
yeah
now what about i mean news reporters for
instance are very iffy with math and uh
you know finance so and even i mean i
can i can also imagine for other sectors
right so uh do uh people i mean uh
do they need uh
some background in finance and business
to do this type of job
this this is what we train and this is
the this is why we have an incredibly
robust not just recruitment but training
we have a very detailed 100 day
onboarding program we also roll the 100
days out goes further with continuous
training through their first year into
the second year into the third year
particularly as they go to different
stages we then train them as they're
about to if they choose to go into
leadership positions and we train them
to look at to be prepared to be as a
leader we work with external
organizations to continue to support
this is a very full and very robust
industry and what what this does is
allows us to make sure that anybody
coming in who's willing to learn hungry
to learn and willing to actually make a
difference we can absolutely train and
we can help them get there um so there
is an assumption that you have to be a
finance major to be able to work in life
insurance no you don't what you need to
do is be willing to learn be willing to
uh try be willing to fail and also
reflect on what didn't work to be able
to be successful and it's thou that
willingness that resilience i think is
really important um so rest assured you
don't necessarily have to have a finance
uh background
does it help possibly it does help um
and for sure it depends very much on the
person but i still think that one of the
key values is the ability to really
really hear your customers properly i
think if you do that this can be an
industry uh that can that can serve you
for a very long time
okay and finally i'm sure our our
watchers are curious uh what are the
perks
uh working in uh life insurance uh as
compared to their previous industries um
uh give us a little uh a little hint
sure sure i mean i think there are a
couple of sides let me look at it from
an industry perspective then i can talk
about the manual life perspective from
an industry perspective you have
flexibility um your flexibility with
your time flexibility around um you know
how you uh how you manage your time now
we advise and we give a lot of support
on the best ways to manage the time
but there's but this for many people if
they choose to take an evening they
choose to do on the weekend they choose
the jury during the week this gives them
that flexibility there's not necessarily
a clocking clock out type of structure
once you've gone through your training
and once you're licensed and you're
ready to uh ready to kind of uh be
servicing your customers so you have
that added flexibility um at the same
time uh the income opportunities are can
be quite significant because the ability
there is no limit because time is and
you're not limited by time there is no
limit to how much you can actually grow
and build up your business and build up
your clientele base and that really does
give you quite a significant opportunity
quite a significant
advantage over many other industries now
to add on to that uh one of some of the
perks that we see in manulife is partly
the recruitment and the training in a
development program that we have very
robust very well tested across all of
our markets we've taken best practice
we've applied it here and we continue to
refine it and tweak it really as the
next generations come through but also
as an organization we absolutely value
inclusivity it is so much a core of who
we are diversity equity and inclusion is
one of our key brand values and what is
important for us is really as we try and
develop our people we develop them so
that they are inclusive of everybody
because everyone comes from a variety of
different backgrounds everybody comes
from a variety of different uh and
customers have different needs if you're
not able to understand the different
diversity of the customer base it
becomes very difficult to also uh
service and support them as well and so
from from our perspective we do you know
our kind of a global global tagline
being every day better it's absolutely
important and critical that for our
individuals and our life
life insurance advisors they really do
go out there and genuinely make every
day better for everybody else
okay and on that note uh i guess uh for
those that have lost their jobs uh maybe
they could consider uh
working for life insurance and uh
manulife and on that note thanks so much
richard bates manulife philippines
president and ceo and i hope you really
get to uh travel the country uh once the
pandemic uh ends or at least the
restrictions uh loosen up a little more
and i will
thanks for watching